<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kunal&apos;s Blog</title>
    <description>Blog about my experiences with data and other technologies.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>2023-08-27</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 07:45:43 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Book Review - Black Swan by Nassim Taleb</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;During the winter break I had a chance to read Black Swan by Nassim. In a world full of uncertainity, “The Black Swan” shines a light on new ideas, shaking up what we think we know about randomness and unpredictability. I would recommend anyone working in field dealing with randomness and complex events to read this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, “The Black Swan” introduces the concept of highly improbable events that defy our expectations, yet wield immense impact on our lives and societies. These “black swan” events, characterized by their rarity and extreme consequences disrupt the &lt;strong&gt;illusion that these events would never happen to us and that the world is stable&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog, I’ll share 6 concept which I found very useful and see how they affect everything from money to history to disasters. “The Black Swan” warns us about &lt;strong&gt;ignoring rare stuff&lt;/strong&gt; and relying too much on plans that usually don’t work in the long run. I have added the page numbers for anyone interested in reading the concepts themself (&lt;strong&gt;paperback second edition&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;problem-of-induction-pg-40&quot;&gt;Problem of Induction (Pg 40):&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “problem of induction,” &lt;strong&gt;challenges the reliability of making predictions based on past experiences or data&lt;/strong&gt;. Traditional methods of induction, which assume that the future will resemble the past, often fail to account for rare and unpredictable events, or “black swans.” This skepticism about induction highlights &lt;strong&gt;how tough it is to predict the future, especially in complex systems&lt;/strong&gt;. He explains this from a point of view of a Turkey which is fed every day which increases the bird’s belief that its a geenral rule of life to be fed everyday. On the Thanksgiving day, the bird has a revision of belief. He explains that &lt;strong&gt;as our feeling of safety increases over time, our risk of failing is also increasing which we tend to ignore&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;confirmation-bias-pg-57&quot;&gt;Confirmation Bias (Pg 57):&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confirmation bias refers to our tendency to seek out and interpret information in a way that confirms our pre-existing beliefs or hypotheses&lt;/strong&gt;. Taleb argues that confirmation bias can lead us to overlook evidence that contradicts our views and can blind us to the possibility of rare and unexpected events, such as black swan events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In hypothesis testing, we tend to look for instances where the hypothesis we were looking for proved true&lt;/strong&gt;. Sometimes a lot of data can be meaningless; at other times one single piece of information can be very meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;narrative-fallacy-pg-63&quot;&gt;Narrative Fallacy (Pg 63):&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Narrative fallacy refers to our inclination to create explanations for random or unpredictable events after they have happened&lt;/strong&gt;. Taleb suggests that humans have a natural tendency to seek meaning and causality in events, even when none truly exists. This tendency can lead us to oversimplify complex phenomena, ignore randomness, and underestimate the role of chance in shaping outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like stories and we like to summarize and simplify things i.e. reduce dimensionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;distortion-bias-silent-evidence-problem-pg-101&quot;&gt;Distortion Bias (Silent evidence problem) (Pg 101):&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distortion bias is when we distort or misrepresent information to fit our existing beliefs or preferences. For example, if we think a certain diet pill works, we might only pay attention to stories that support that idea and ignore ones that say it doesn’t work. This can make us stick to our beliefs even when there’s evidence against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;reference-point-argument-pg-119&quot;&gt;Reference point argument (Pg 119):&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reference point argument means that our perceptions and judgments are heavily influenced by the reference points we use to evaluate outcomes. Humans tend to compare outcomes to a specific reference point or baseline, which can distort their perceptions of risk and reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if someone invests in the stock market and their portfolio increases by 10%, they might perceive this as a positive outcome if their reference point is the initial investment amount. However, if their reference point is a higher level of return, such as 15%, they might perceive the 10% gain as a disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;anchoring-pg-158&quot;&gt;Anchoring (Pg 158):&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anchoring (&lt;em&gt;research from Daniel Kahneman and Amos&lt;/em&gt;) is a cognitive bias where individuals rely heavily on the first piece of information they encounter (the “anchor”) when making decisions or judgments. This initial piece of information then influences subsequent decisions, even if it’s unrelated or irrelevant to the decision at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, imagine you’re negotiating the price of a used car. The seller suggests a price of $15,000, which becomes your anchor point. Even if you know the car is overpriced based on market research, the $15,000 figure may still influence your perception of what constitutes a fair price, leading you to make an offer that’s closer to the anchor than you otherwise would have.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2024-02-03</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2024-02/black-swan</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2024-02/black-swan</guid>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
        <category>statistics</category>
        
        <category>randomness</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How JIT (and not git) impacts your code workflow</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;JIT stands for &lt;strong&gt;“Just-In-Time”&lt;/strong&gt; compilation, which is a technique used by some programming languages and runtime environments to improve the performance of executing code. That would make sense to a developer but for non-developer, I think the definition can be a bit confusing so let me try to explain this in a simple way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you have a code blob written in your fav programming language (&lt;em&gt;let’s say python for now&lt;/em&gt;). Now Python is an &lt;strong&gt;interpreted programming language&lt;/strong&gt;, which means that the source code is executed line by line by a Python interpreter at runtime. Your machine can only understand binary numbers so python interpreter helps bridge the gap between your python code and the machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to &lt;strong&gt;Python’s dynamic nature&lt;/strong&gt; and the way it handles data types, pure interpretation can result in relatively slower execution speeds compared to languages that are compiled to machine code directly (For example C, C++) which are signficantly faster to run. For more context on how compilation works, check this &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@bdov_/what-happens-when-you-type-gcc-main-c-a4454564e96d&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to python(&lt;em&gt;our selected programming language&lt;/em&gt;) which is interpreted at run time, our computer has to translate the python code into machine readable code which can be very slow if we have to many recurring function calls or loops (&lt;em&gt;every function call has to be translated to machine code before executing&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;demo-code-&quot;&gt;Demo code: 🧪💻💥&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me show the above issue with an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you have a very basic python code file (&lt;em&gt;say sum.py&lt;/em&gt;), which &lt;strong&gt;runs a loop to add 2 numbers in loop running 1000 times&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def sum(a,b):
        return a+b

for i in range(0,1000):
        sum(i,i+1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can run the above code using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;time python sum.py&lt;/code&gt; to get ideas on the time it took to execute the above code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 1000 iterations, it takes &lt;strong&gt;0.03 sec&lt;/strong&gt; on Mac pro with 32 GB ram and intel processor:
&lt;img width=&quot;1012&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/tDbN1hp/nromal-1000.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s crank the number of iteration to 100 M, the same code takes &lt;strong&gt;14.5 secs&lt;/strong&gt; to run 🤯 🦥 🐢&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;1012&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/9gd1fzH/normal-execution.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;magic-of-jit&quot;&gt;Magic of JIT&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JIT can significantly help improve python runtime performance. It uses a technique called “tracing JIT” to identify frequently executed code paths and optimize them. &lt;strong&gt;JIT can detect any recurring function during the execution&lt;/strong&gt; and store a compiled version on the fly. During the execution, JIT will start using the compiled function instead of parsing and interpreting the function during the loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our example, JIT will detect that the function &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sum(a,b)&lt;/code&gt; is being called in a loop multiple times. &lt;strong&gt;Why not compile it on the fly and use the compiled version for execution which might save some CPU cycles.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;jit-in-action-example&quot;&gt;JIT in action example:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am using pypy3 package to run JIT but you can try other packages too (Numba etc). To install pypy3 use the below command in mac:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew install pypy3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 100M iterations, it takes &lt;strong&gt;0.16 sec&lt;/strong&gt; to run the same code with JIT (&lt;strong&gt;98.8% faster than python code without JIT&lt;/strong&gt; 🚀🚀🏃🏃)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;1012&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/28NB9vJ/with-jit.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen the benefits of JIT in a language like python where it can help speed up the execution times signficantly, but there are some &lt;strong&gt;limitations of JIT&lt;/strong&gt; which I wanted to share here as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JIT has a higher memory overhead than usual runtime. Since we have to store the compiled code in the machine which takes up memory, running JIT on a code base with too many functions would need significantly high memory compared to normal python operations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JIT works well with long running programs. For programs with not a lot of loops/functions, the memory overhead of running JIT is not worth the effort.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It doesn’t do Ahead-Of-Time Compilation (AOT) like C where a program is compiled before running. It compiles the code during runtime but there is no support to pre-compile the code in advance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think JIT can significantly boost the performance of your code base and if you have long running loops, you should conisder it. In Shopify, we use have seen signficant speedups in code compilation using &lt;a href=&quot;https://shopify.engineering/yjit-just-in-time-compiler-cruby&quot;&gt;YJIT&lt;/a&gt; which is similar to JIT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more context on JIT using pypy, check this &lt;a href=&quot;https://realpython.com/pypy-faster-python/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any questions, reach out on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/kunal-kohli-a8815b80/&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2023-08-27</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2023-08/jit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2023-08/jit</guid>
        
        
        <category>web_perf</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Creating Blog using Jekyll</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I always wanted a blog where I can put my ideas and projects I am doing and get feedback from people. I tried creating a rails app which would host my pages but due to lack of time I couldn’t give much time to it. Finally I found Jekyll (recommended to me by my lead @ Shopify) which not just lets you create blog website but also lets you host sites right from your GitHub repositories. There are a lot of websites out there which can help you create a blog by dragging and dropping elements but my idea of blog was not just to share my views with people but to also learn web development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in learning &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll&lt;/code&gt;, feel free to check this post and share your views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jekyll&lt;/b&gt; is a static site generator. You give it text written in your favorite markup language and it uses layouts to create a static website. You can tweak how you want the site URLs to look like, what data gets displayed on the site, and more. Jekyll does what you tell it to do — no more, no less. It doesn’t try to outsmart users by making bold assumptions, nor does it burden them with needless complexity and configuration. Put simply, Jekyll gets out of your way and allows you to concentrate on what truly matters: your content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;install Jekyll - run this command in terminal to install jekyll (mac)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;      gem &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install &lt;/span&gt;jekyll bundler
    &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selecting theme for the blog &lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllthemes.io/jekyll-blog-themes&quot;&gt;Jekyll Themes&lt;/a&gt; to check all the themes available for use. you can also preview how a theme looks by clicking the theme and clicking live demo.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Once you have decide the theme, click on the github repo to get the link to copy the cloning link as shown in red below.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/VWFmg86/Screen-Shot-2020-01-01-at-8-24-51-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; style=&quot;width:450px;height:170px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Now go to terminal and enter the below command:&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;          git clone &amp;lt;copied_link&amp;gt;
        &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the repository has been cloned, do a cd into it and run the below command:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;    bundle &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install
    &lt;/span&gt;bundle &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exec &lt;/span&gt;jekyll serve
  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fire up a browser and open the below link:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;  
    http://localhost:4000/
  
  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To add things to the resume section, edit the following files:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;  
    1. For about section : edit about.yml in _includes/sections/
    2. For career section : edit careers.yml in _data/index/
    3. For education section : edit education.yml in _data/index/
    4. For projects section : edit projects.yml in _data/index/
    5. For skills section : edit skills.yml in _data/index/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To change the image, blog name and add social media on the homepage, edit &lt;b&gt;_config.yml &lt;/b&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To add a new blog post, just add a blank markdown with the name of your choice inside &lt;b&gt;_posts/ &lt;/b&gt;, and then add content to it&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;run the server to see if the changes you did are visible on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll-help&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s dedicated Help repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>2023-08-27</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2020-01/welcome-to-jekyll</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2020-01/welcome-to-jekyll</guid>
        
        
        <category>tutorial</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
